Finding Aid for the Norris Poulson Papers LSC.0787
UCLA Library Special Collections
Norris Poulson papers
1938-1976
UCLA Library Special Collections
Poulson, Norris
LSC.0787
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes and 23 oversize boxes)
Charles Norris Poulson (1895-1982) was elected and served in the California State Assembly (1938-42), was elected to the House of Representatives in 1942, served as mayor of Los Angeles (1953-61), and was a member of the California Water Commission (1965-68). The collection consists of scrapbooks, clippings, documents, correspondence, photographs, and memorabilia related to the life of Norris Poulson including Poulson's autobiography, and materials related to his career as a California assemblyman, U.S. Congressman, and Los Angeles mayor.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Norris Poulson, 1966 & 1976.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942336083606533
Biography
Charles Norris Poulson was born on July 23, 1895; attended Oregon Agricultural College, 1914-15; farmed 1916-23; moved to Los Angeles in 1923; attended Southwestern University, 1923-25; began his own accounting business about 1925, passing the California CPA examination in 1933; was elected and served in the California State Assembly (1938-42); first elected to the House of Representatives in 1942; served as mayor of Los Angeles (1953-61); served as a member of the California Water Commission (1965-68); he died on September 25, 1982.
Chronology
Missing Title
July 23, 1895 Born Charles Norris Poulson, Baker County, Oregon
Fall 1913 Attended Oregon Agricultural College
Fall 1914 Attended business college in Baker City, Oregon
February, 1915 Became accountant for J.F. Bryant, Haines, Oregon
December 25, 1916 Married Erna June Loennig
1916-1923 Farmed in Baker County, Oregon
Spring 1923 Moved to Los Angeles, California; became a bookkeeper for Square Oil Company
ca. 1925 Began accounting business of his own
1933 Passed California CPA examination
1938 Elected to the California State Assembly for the Los Angeles 56th District
1939 Investigated the California Athletic Comm.
1940 Re-elected to the California State Assembly
November, 1942 Elected to the U.S. House of Representatives for the California 13th District
November, 1944 Lost the congressional race for re-election to Ned Healy
1945 State lobbyist for California CPA Association
November, 1946 Elected to the U.S. House of Representatives
1948, 1950, 1952 Re-elected to serve as Representative; served on the House Public Lands Comm. (now the Interior Comm.)
December, 1952-May, 1953 Campaigned as Los Angeles mayoralty candidate against Fletcher Bowron
May 26, 1953 Elected mayor of Los Angeles
July, 1953 Settled the Los Angeles Public Housing issue
1956 Involved in the Los Angeles rubbish issue; served as a delegate to the Republican National Convention for Richard M. Nixon
1957 Was re-elected mayor of Los Angeles
1957-1959 Involved in the Los Angeles Major League Baseball issue
September, 1959 Hosted Premier Nikita Khrushchev during his visit to Los Angeles
1961 Lost the mayoralty election to Samuel Yorty
1965-1968 Served as member of the California Water Commission, participating in the California bond issue.
1969- Retired and residing in Tustin, California
Scope and Content
Collection consists of scrapbooks, clippings, documents, correspondence, photographs, memorabilia, and related material of former Los Angeles mayor Norris Poulson. Includes Poulson's autobiography, The genealogy and life story of Erna and Norris Poulson. Includes materials related to his career as a California assemblyman, U.S. Congressman, and Los Angeles mayor, as well as signed letters and photographs of Dwight D. Eisenhower, Richard M. Nixon, Mayor Fletcher Bowron, Mayor Samuel Yorty, Nikita Khrushchev, Earl Warren, and others.
Expanded Scope and Content
Norris Poulson's career as a California Assemblyman, Representative and member of the House Committee on Public Lands, and mayor of Los Angeles spans the time period 1938-1961. The Collection of his papers consists, in the greater part, of 39 scrapbooks containing clippings and memorabilia covering Poulson's political career. The majority of the material covers Poulson's two terms as mayor. There is very little correspondence of a personal or official nature, but there are many letters signed by prominent political figures, foreign dignitaries, and celebrities.
Particularly of interest are the extensive materials concerned with the California/Arizona water issue, the coverage of Nikita Khrushchev's visit to Los Angeles, and materials pertaining to the Los Angeles Dodgers and the Chavez Ravine deal with Walter O'Malley.
As Congressman and Mayor, Poulson knew and associated with many prominent political figures and citizens. As Mayor Poulson met and hosted many celebrities and foreign dignitaries. The Collection contains many signed letters from and photographs of prominent people. Of note are: Dwight D. Eisenhower, Richard M. Nixon, Mayor Fletcher Bowron, Mayor Samuel Yorty, Nikita Khrushchev, Earl Warren, and others.
Also included in the Collection is an autobiography "The Genealogy and Life Story of Erna and Norris Poulson." The autobiography, like Poulson's oral history "Who would have ever dreamed," gives detailed accounts of Poulson's political career.
Related Oral History
The following oral history is available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Interview of Norris Poulson
Scrapbooks.; Mayors -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Legislators -- United States -- Archives.; Poulson, Norris -- Archives
- Congressman Poulson's newsletter to constituents., 1943-1944 & 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
- Remarks of Hon. Norris Poulson: 81st Congress, 2nd session., 1950 (Box 1)
- Remarks of Hon. Norris Poulson: 83rd Congress, 1st session., 1953 (Box 1)
- Correspondence., 1953 (Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Primarily congratulatory letters and telegrams after Poulson's election as mayor of Los Angeles.
  General note
  Folders 1-21, alphabetically arranged.
  See also package 15 for additional letters.
- City of Los Angeles., ca. 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Added and improved services; operating economies and efficiencies; additional development of city services and facilities., ca. 1960; (26 leaves, typescript carbon) (Box 2)
  - Capital improvement program accomplishments July 1, 1953 to December 31, 1960., ca. 1961; (Typescript) (Box 2)
- "Transcript of preliminary investigation into the matter of rubbish collection in the City of Los Angeles.", June 20-28, 1955; (3 copies, photocopy) (Box 3)
- Poulson - Yorty campaign for mayor., 1961 (Box 4)
  Box contains mostly clippings, some correspondence, transcripts of radio and T.V. interviews, etc. Though arranged in 13 labeled folders, these materials have not really been organized and sifted for duplicates.
- Miscellaneous., 1940-1976 (Box 5)
  For additions, see page 7
- Printed memorabilia found loose in Scrapbook 2 "Dad's First Session - California Legislature" (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Trip to the Mandated Islands., February 1947; (pp.86-101, photocopy) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  From Poulson's oral history "Who would have ever dreamed?"
- The Poulson's European Trip (2 copies)., July-August 1952; (Typescript carbon, 26 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous - personal., 1947-1965 (Box 5, Folder 4-7)
  Clippings, photographs, printed memorabilia, and correspondence.
- Correspondence., 1964-1975 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  Letters to and from Wayne Aspinall, former democratic Representative from Colorado
  Letters from Wayne D'Ewart, Republican Representative from Colorado
  Miscellaneous personal correspondence
- "The Genealogy and Life Story of Erna and Norris Poulson" by Norris Poulson, (Bound copy, 311pp.) (Box 5)
  This was written January 1974-ca. 1976 as a keepsake for Poulson's children and grandchildren. Much of the text repeats parts of his oral history "Who would have ever dreamed?" completed by the UCLA Oral History Program in 1966.
- Mainly scrapbooks containing congratulatory letters, printed memorabilia, clippings, photographs, family memorabilia and souvenirs, correspondence, etc. (Box 5)
- Assembly campaign., 1938 (Box 6)
- Athletic Commission investigation., 1938 (Box 6)
- Dad's First Session - California Legislature., 1938-1940 (Box 7)
- Assembly campaign for re-election., 1940 (Box 7)
- Assembly memorabilia., 1941 (Box 8)
- Congressional campaign., 1942 (Box 8)
- Congressional clippings and memorabilia., 1943 (Box 8)
- Congressional campaign for re-election against Ned Healy., May-November 1944 (Box 9)
- Congressional campaign and clippings., November-May 1945 (Box 9)
- Congressional campaign., June-December 1946 (Box 10)
- Congressional memorabilia and Mandated Islands Trip., 1947 (Box 10)
- Congressional campaign., 1948 (Box 6)
- California/Arizona water issue., 1948-1949 (Box 11)
- Congressional campaign and water issue., 1948-1950 (Box 11)
- Congressional memorabilia and campaign., 1949-1950 (Box 12)
- Congressional campaign and water issue., 1950 (Box 12)
- Water issue., January-July 1951 (Box 13)
- Water issue and re-election., August 1951-1952 (Box 13)
- "Mayor's race, Book 1.", December 26, 1952-March 15, 1953 (Box 14)
- "Mayor's race, Book 2.", March 14-April 6, 1953 (Box 14)
- "Mayor's race, Book 3.", April 7-May 6, 1953 (Box 15)
- "Mayor's race, Book 4.", May 7-19, 1953 (Box 15)
- "Mayor's race, Book 5.", May 20-26, 1953 (Box 16)
- "Mayor's race, Book 6.", May 26-28, 1953 (Box 16)
  Includes election returns.
- Souvenirs and printed memorabilia., January-May 1953 (Box 17)
- "Mayor Elect.", May 28-June 27, 1953 (Box 17)
- "Congratulatory letters and telegrams.", 1953-1957 (Box 15)
  For additional letters see Box 2, folders 1-21.
- "Newspaper Clippings, Book 1.", June 1953-December 1958 (Box 18)
- "Newspaper Clippings, Book 2.", December 1958-September 1965 (Box 19)
- "Correspondence.", June 1953-December 1975 (Box 20)
  Letters received by Poulson during his two terms as mayor of Los Angeles and thereafter, often from famous politicians or celebrities. Some of the more notable are:
  Willi Brandt, leaves 21
  Gov. Edmund Brown, leaves 62, 63, 64
  Pres. Dwight D. Eisenhower, leaves 2, 15, 21a, 25, 27
  Mamie Eisenhower, leaves 3, 7
  Senator John F. Kennedy, leaves 22
  Gov. Goodwin Knight, leaves 8, 10, 15
  Nikita Khrushchev, leaves 80
  V.P. Richard M. Nixon, leaves 4, 7, 8, 9, 41
  Speaker Sam Rayburn, leaves 9
  Edward Rickenbacker, leaves 36
  Nelson D. Rockefellar, leaves 65
  Pres. Harry S. Truman, leaves 5, 18, 21a
  Mrs. Bess Truman, leaves 5
  Chief Justice Earl Warren, leaf 1, 2
  John Wayne, leaves 19
- Photographs., March 1957-June 1961 (Box 20)
  (Photographs of Mayor Poulson attending public functions during his second term. Mayor Poulson is often photographed with famous persons; some of the more notable are:
  Willi Brandt, leaves 33, 34
  King Hussein of Jordan, leaves 52
  John F. Kennedy, leaves 60
  Nikita Khrushchev, leaves 49
  Richard M. Nixon, leaves 17, 50, 57
  Nelson D. Rockefeller, leaves 57
  Earl Warren, leaves 29
- Souvenirs of Trips Made - Civic Functions for distinguished visitors - Important Affairs, Book 1.", 1940-September 1957 (Box 21)
- Souvenirs of Trips Made - Civic Functions for distinguished visitors - Important Affairs, Book 2.", September 1958-June 1961 (Box 21)
- Souvenirs, Remembrances from friends and family, etc., Book 1.", 1913-1960 (Box 22)
- "Souvenirs, Remembrances from friends and family, etc., Book 2.", 1960-1961 (Box 22)
- Miscellaneous letters, clippings, souvenirs., 1940-June 1976 (Box 23)
- "Honorable Norris Poulson, in print. By Joseph Niemiec. vol.1.", May-August 1953 (Box 24)
  The three volumes in this series include clippings from Poulson's first term as mayor but also many clippings from popular newspaper and magazine columns such as "Ripley's Believe It or Not."
- "Honorable Norris Poulson, in print. By Joseph Niemiec. vol.2.", August-December 1953 (Box 25)
- "Honorable Norris Poulson, in print. By Joseph Niemiec. vol.3.", January-June 1954 (Box 26)
- Port of Los Angeles - Annual Reports., 1952-1960 (Box 27)
- Los Angeles Dodgers., 1961 (Box 27)
  Photo Album with autographs.
- Los Angeles Examiner: "Los Angeles Reports to its Citizens.", 1956-1960; (5 vol.) (Box 28)
- Los Angeles Times: "Midwinter Edition.", 1956-1958; (3 vol.) (Box 28)
- Flight: A Pictorial History of Aviation by the Editors of Year., 1953 (Box 9)
- Eisenhower Presidential Inauguration., January 20, 1953 (Box 16)
  This scrapbook includes clippings and souvenirs from all the inaugural functions.
- Southern California Quarterly (vol.62, no.3) (Box 5)
  Contains article: Cary S. Henderson. "Los Angeles and the Dodger War, 1957-1962," pp.261-286, which Mr. Poulson requested be added to his reminiscences.